<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Content: Content-addressed reference layer for the clayers format.
  Describes the content layer and its role as a foundation primitive
  for integrity-verified references to external or embedded content.
-->
<spec:clayers xmlns:spec="urn:clayers:spec"
       xmlns:pr="urn:clayers:prose"
       xmlns:trm="urn:clayers:terminology"
       xmlns:cnt="urn:clayers:content"
       xmlns:org="urn:clayers:organization"
       xmlns:rel="urn:clayers:relation"
       xmlns:art="urn:clayers:artifact"
       xmlns:llm="urn:clayers:llm"
       spec:index="index.xml">

  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!-- Content Layer                                                       -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <pr:section id="content-layer">
    <pr:title>Content Layer</pr:title>
    <pr:shortdesc>General-purpose content-addressed references with hash
    integrity and three access modes.</pr:shortdesc>

    <pr:p>Specifications refer to content beyond their own XML: test fixtures,
    configuration fragments, images, external documents. The content layer
    provides a uniform mechanism for these references. Each
    <pr:code>cnt:content</pr:code> node identifies content by a cryptographic
    hash, guaranteeing integrity regardless of where the content lives.</pr:p>

    <pr:p>Three modes cover the spectrum of content locality. In
    <pr:b>referenced</pr:b> mode, a URL points to the canonical external
    location and the hash verifies its integrity on fetch. In
    <pr:b>embedded</pr:b> mode, a <pr:code>cnt:body</pr:code> child contains
    the content inline and the hash verifies the embedded copy. In
    <pr:b>both</pr:b> mode, the URL provides the canonical location while the
    body holds a local copy, with the hash binding both to the same content.
    An XSD 1.1 assertion enforces that at least one of URL or body is present,
    making empty content nodes structurally impossible.</pr:p>

    <pr:p>The <pr:code>cnt:ref</pr:code> element enables inline references to
    content nodes from within prose, parallel to <pr:code>trm:ref</pr:code>
    for terminology and <pr:code>src:cite</pr:code> for sources. Its
    <pr:code>content</pr:code> attribute is an IDREF pointing to a
    <pr:code>cnt:content</pr:code> element's ID, and its mixed content provides
    display text.</pr:p>

    <pr:p>The content layer is a foundation primitive. The testing layer builds
    on it to attach test fixtures and expected outputs to spec nodes. The source
    layer will eventually use it to embed or reference cited material with
    integrity guarantees. Any layer that needs to point at content beyond inline
    XML text can use <pr:code>cnt:content</pr:code> as its substrate.</pr:p>
  </pr:section>

  <org:concept ref="content-layer">
    <org:purpose>Understanding the content layer as a general-purpose,
    content-addressed reference mechanism with three access modes (referenced,
    embedded, both), hash integrity, and inline references via cnt:ref.</org:purpose>
  </org:concept>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!-- Terminology                                                         -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <trm:term id="type-content">
    <trm:name>ContentType</trm:name>
    <trm:definition>The XSD complexType that defines the structure of content
    nodes in the content layer: id, url, hash, optional media-type, and an
    optional body child for embedded content.</trm:definition>
  </trm:term>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!-- Relations                                                           -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <!-- Content layer refines the layered architecture -->
  <rel:relation type="refines" from="content-layer" to="layered-architecture">
    <rel:note>The content layer adds content-addressed references as a
    semantic dimension within the layered architecture.</rel:note>
  </rel:relation>

  <!-- Schema type node connects to the content layer -->
  <rel:relation type="refines" from="type-content" to="content-layer">
    <rel:note>The ContentType complexType (id="type-content") is the schema
    definition for content nodes in the content layer.</rel:note>
  </rel:relation>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!-- LLM descriptions                                                    -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <llm:node ref="content-layer">
    Describes the content layer: general-purpose content-addressed references
    with hash integrity. Three modes: referenced (url + hash for external
    canonical locations), embedded (body + hash for inline content), or both
    (url for canonical, body for local copy). The cnt:ref element enables
    inline references to content nodes from prose, parallel to trm:ref and
    src:cite. Foundation primitive used by the testing layer for test fixtures
    and eventually by the source layer for cited material with integrity
    guarantees.
  </llm:node>

  <!-- Out-of-band schema descriptions for the content layer -->
  <llm:schema namespace="urn:clayers:content">
    The content schema provides content-addressed references with integrity
    guarantees. Each &lt;cnt:content&gt; node identifies content by hash with
    three modes: referenced (url + hash for external canonical locations),
    embedded (body + hash for inline content), or both. The hash attribute
    ensures integrity regardless of mode. The &lt;cnt:ref&gt; element enables
    inline references to content nodes from prose, parallel to trm:ref and
    src:cite. BodyType supports text, CDATA, base64 (via encoding attribute),
    and structured XML via xs:any.
  </llm:schema>

  <llm:schema namespace="urn:clayers:content" element="content">
    A content-addressed reference node. The id makes it addressable in the
    spec graph. The hash attribute provides integrity verification. Three
    modes: referenced (url points to external canonical location), embedded
    (body child contains inline content), or both (url for canonical location,
    body for local copy). At least one of url or body must be present,
    enforced by XSD 1.1 assertion. The optional media-type classifies the
    content format.
  </llm:schema>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!-- Artifact mappings and exemptions                                    -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <!-- Documentation-only concept -->
  <art:exempt node="content-layer">Conceptual documentation describing the
  content layer's purpose and design. No code implements this concept.</art:exempt>

  <!-- Type to schema mapping -->
  <art:mapping id="map-type-content-schema">
    <art:spec-ref node="type-content"
              revision="draft-1"
              node-hash="sha256:9a7586f080fb0b0af9f02e69499876f7c22c5a49e07ef61a26de118d48c8c88d"/>
    <art:artifact repo="repo-clayers"
              repo-revision="e5fa37e"
              path="schemas/content.xsd">
        <art:range hash="sha256:4ac06806fded45b09bc6848860cfcb7e63a7213d0e3e5622db00652c6a722af8" start-line="55" end-line="99"/>
      </art:artifact>
    <art:coverage>full</art:coverage>
    <art:note>ContentType complexType: id, url, hash, media-type, optional body child.</art:note>
  </art:mapping>

</spec:clayers>
