<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  LLM Descriptions: Machine-readable descriptions for language models.
  How the LLM layer works in-band and out-of-band.
-->
<spec:clayers xmlns:spec="urn:clayers:spec"
       xmlns:pr="urn:clayers:prose"
       xmlns:org="urn:clayers:organization"
       xmlns:rel="urn:clayers:relation"
       xmlns:art="urn:clayers:artifact"
       xmlns:llm="urn:clayers:llm"
       spec:index="index.xml">

  <!-- Content -->

  <pr:section id="llm-layer">
    <pr:title>LLM Descriptions</pr:title>
    <pr:shortdesc>Machine-readable descriptions embedded in schemas and layer
    files for language model consumption.</pr:shortdesc>

    <pr:p>The LLM layer provides descriptions optimized for language models. It
    operates in two modes that serve different purposes:</pr:p>

    <pr:ul>
      <pr:li><pr:b>Out-of-band</pr:b> (llm.xml): a layer file containing two element
      types. <pr:code>node</pr:code> elements describe spec nodes by ID reference
      (validated via keyref in the combined schema). <pr:code>schema</pr:code>
      elements describe schemas or specific schema elements by namespace URI,
      with an optional element attribute to narrow the scope. This follows the
      standard layer-file pattern with independent evolution.</pr:li>
      <pr:li><pr:b>In-band</pr:b> (inside XSD files): <pr:code>llm:describe</pr:code>
      elements placed inside <pr:code>xs:appinfo</pr:code> annotations, co-located
      with the schema elements they describe. Any XSD can import the LLM
      namespace and add descriptions to its type definitions, element
      declarations, or top-level annotations.</pr:li>
    </pr:ul>

    <pr:p>The two modes complement each other. In-band descriptions travel with
    the schema and are available to any tool that reads the XSD. Out-of-band
    descriptions can reference nodes from any layer without modifying those
    layers, and can evolve independently of the schemas they describe.</pr:p>

    <pr:p>The layer is self-describing: llm.xsd contains in-band descriptions of
    its own elements via xs:appinfo, and the clayers's llm.xml includes
    out-of-band descriptions of all schemas including itself.</pr:p>
  </pr:section>

  <!-- Topic typing -->

  <org:concept ref="llm-layer">
    <org:purpose>Understanding how LLM descriptions work in-band and out-of-band,
    and why the layer is self-describing.</org:purpose>
  </org:concept>

  <!-- Relations -->

  <rel:relation type="refines" from="llm-layer" to="layered-architecture">
    <rel:note>The LLM layer is one of the layers in the architecture, with a
    unique dual-mode design (in-band and out-of-band).</rel:note>
  </rel:relation>

  <!-- Artifact mappings -->

  <art:mapping id="map-llm-layer">
    <art:spec-ref node="llm-layer"
              revision="draft-1"
              node-hash="sha256:85b9dc69cf6f7c2c1c811af6a62f15c30c6286daa6c1c56a48ca8b501cfe2f92"/>
    <art:artifact repo="repo-clayers"
              repo-revision="ae7434a"
              path="schemas/llm.xsd">
        <art:range hash="sha256:77d4c8fee44bfcad36365d51af8919c1e3f25470c95dfeb055b0c9b0e2b364a3"/>
      </art:artifact>
    <art:coverage>full</art:coverage>
    <art:note>llm.xsd defines both the out-of-band elements (node, schema) and
    the in-band describe element. The schema is self-describing via its own
    appinfo annotations.</art:note>
  </art:mapping>

  <!-- Machine descriptions -->

  <llm:schema namespace="urn:clayers:llm">
    The LLM layer embeds descriptions optimized for language model
    consumption. Two element types: &lt;node&gt; describes a spec node
    by ID reference (validated via keyref), and &lt;schema&gt; describes
    a schema or a specific schema element by namespace URI. This layer
    is self-describing: it contains a description of its own schema.
    Use it to provide context about what each element means, how to
    use it, and how it relates to other elements.
  </llm:schema>

  <llm:schema namespace="urn:clayers:llm" element="node">
    Describes a spec node for LLM consumption. The ref attribute is a
    node ID (validated against the unified ID space). The text content
    should explain what the node means, how it relates to other nodes,
    and any guidance for interpreting or modifying it.
  </llm:schema>

  <llm:schema namespace="urn:clayers:llm" element="schema">
    Describes a schema or a specific element within a schema. The
    namespace attribute is the schema's namespace URI. The optional
    element attribute narrows the description to a specific element
    within that schema. When element is omitted, the description
    applies to the schema as a whole.
  </llm:schema>

  <llm:node ref="llm-layer">
    Describes the LLM layer's dual-mode design: in-band descriptions
    inside xs:appinfo in XSD files, and out-of-band descriptions in
    llm.xml with node (by ID) and schema (by namespace) elements. The
    layer is self-describing. Key for understanding how to add LLM
    guidance to new schemas or spec nodes.
  </llm:node>
</spec:clayers>
